<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="https://chandra.harvard.edu/incl/css/photo_xml_css.css" type="text/css"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Chandra :: Photo Album</title>
<link>https://chandra.harvard.edu/photo/</link>
<description>Chandra Photo Album :: Recent Discoveries</description>
<language>en-us</language>
	<item>
		<title>NASA's IXPE Helps Unlock the Secrets of Famous Exploded Star</title>
		<link>https://chandra.harvard.edu/photo/2022/casa_streams/</link>
		<guid>https://chandra.harvard.edu/photo/2022/casa_streams/</guid>
		<pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2022 12:00:00 EST</pubDate>
		<description>Astronomers have made the first measurement in X-rays of the polarization from the remains of an exploded star called Cassiopeia A.</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>NASA's Chandra Finds Galaxy Cluster Collision on a "WHIM"</title>
		<link>https://chandra.harvard.edu/photo/2022/a98/</link>
		<guid>https://chandra.harvard.edu/photo/2022/a98/</guid>
		<pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2022 12:00:00 EST</pubDate>
		<description>Astronomers taking inventory of the material in the local universe keep coming up short. A new result from NASA's Chandra X-ray Observatory about a system of colliding galaxy clusters may help explain this shortfall.</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>NASA's Chandra Adds X-ray Vision to Webb Images</title>
		<link>https://chandra.harvard.edu/photo/2022/chandrawebb/</link>
		<guid>https://chandra.harvard.edu/photo/2022/chandrawebb/</guid>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2022 12:00:00 EST</pubDate>
		<description>Images combining Webb infrared data with X-rays collected by Chandra underscore how the power of any of these telescopes is only enhanced when joined with others.</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Setting the Clock on a Stellar Explosion</title>
		<link>https://chandra.harvard.edu/photo/2022/snr0519/</link>
		<guid>https://chandra.harvard.edu/photo/2022/snr0519/</guid>
		<pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 12:00:00 EST</pubDate>
		<description>It is often difficult to determine the timeline of a star's demise. By studying the spectacular remains of a supernova, a team has found enough clues to help wind back the clock.</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>NASA Telescopes Capture Stellar Delivery Service for Black Hole</title>
		<link>https://chandra.harvard.edu/photo/2022/ngc4424/</link>
		<guid>https://chandra.harvard.edu/photo/2022/ngc4424/</guid>
		<pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 12:00:00 EST</pubDate>
		<description>Astronomers may have witnessed a smaller galaxy colliding with a larger spiral galaxy and delivering a supermassive black hole.</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Embracing a Rejected Star</title>
		<link>https://chandra.harvard.edu/photo/2022/zetaoph/</link>
		<guid>https://chandra.harvard.edu/photo/2022/zetaoph/</guid>
		<pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2022 12:00:00 EST</pubDate>
		<description>Zeta Ophiuchi is a star with a complicated past, having likely been ejected from its birthplace by a powerful stellar explosion. A new look by NASA's Chandra X-ray Observatory helps tell more of the story of this runaway star.</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Chandra Shows Giant Black Hole Spins Slower Than Its Peers</title>
		<link>https://chandra.harvard.edu/photo/2022/h1821/</link>
		<guid>https://chandra.harvard.edu/photo/2022/h1821/</guid>
		<pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2022 12:00:00 EST</pubDate>
		<description>Astronomers used NASA's Chandra X-ray Observatory to determine the spin of the black hole in H1821+643, making it the most massive one to have an accurate measurement of this fundamental property.</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>NASA's Chandra Catches Pulsar in X-ray Speed Trap</title>
		<link>https://chandra.harvard.edu/photo/2022/g292/</link>
		<guid>https://chandra.harvard.edu/photo/2022/g292/</guid>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2022 12:00:00 EST</pubDate>
		<description>A young pulsar is blazing through the Milky Way at a speed of over a million miles per hour. This stellar speedster is one of the fastest objects of its kind ever seen.</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Colossal Collisions Linked to Solar System Science</title>
		<link>https://chandra.harvard.edu/photo/2022/a2146/</link>
		<guid>https://chandra.harvard.edu/photo/2022/a2146/</guid>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2022 12:00:00 EST</pubDate>
		<description>A new study shows a deep connection between some of the largest, most energetic events in the Universe and much smaller, weaker ones powered by our own Sun.</description>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>NASA Telescopes Support Event Horizon Telescope in Studying Milky Way's Black Hole</title>
		<link>https://chandra.harvard.edu/photo/2022/sgra/</link>
		<guid>https://chandra.harvard.edu/photo/2022/sgra/</guid>
		<pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 12:00:00 EST</pubDate>
		<description>As the Event Horizon Telescope was collecting data for its remarkable new image of the Milky Way's supermassive black hole, a legion of other telescopes, including Chandra, was also watching.</description>
	</item>
</channel>
</rss>
