<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>New NASA STI Report Series</title><link>https://www.sti.nasa.gov</link><description><![CDATA[Today's Listing of New NASA STI Report Series in the NASA Technical Reports Server (NTRS).]]></description><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2017 07:39:13 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.sti.nasa.gov/scan/rss99-02.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><image><title>New NASA STI Report Series</title><url>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/images/insignia.png</url><link>https://www.sti.nasa.gov</link></image><item><title>Hardware Interface Description for the Integrated Power, Avionics, and Software (iPAS) Space Telecommunications Radio Ssystem (STRS) Radio</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004669</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: The Space Telecommunications Radio System (STRS) provides a common, consistent framework for software defined radios (SDRs) to abstract the application software from the radio platform hardware. The STRS standard aims to reduce the cost and risk of using complex, configurable and reprogrammable radio systems across NASA missions. To promote the use of the STRS architecture for future NASA advanced exploration missions, NASA Glenn Research Center (GRC) developed an STRS-compliant SDR on a radi...]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 30 May 2017 11:13:07 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004669</guid></item><item><title>Programmable Logic Device (PLD) Design Description for the Integrated Power, Avionics, and Software (iPAS) Space Telecommunications Radio System (STRS) Radio</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004668</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: The Space Telecommunications Radio System (STRS) provides a common, consistent framework for software defined radios (SDRs) to abstract the application software from the radio platform hardware. The STRS standard aims to reduce the cost and risk of using complex, configurable and reprogrammable radio systems across NASA missions. To promote the use of the STRS architecture for future NASA advanced exploration missions, NASA Glenn Research Center (GRC) developed an STRS compliant SDR on a radi...]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 30 May 2017 10:49:07 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004668</guid></item><item><title>Incorporation of Failure Into an Orthotropic Three-Dimensional Model with Tabulated Input Suitable for Use in Composite Impact Problems</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004667</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: The need for accurate material models to simulate the deformation, damage and failure of polymer matrix composites under impact conditions is becoming critical as these materials are gaining increased use in the aerospace and automotive communities. The aerospace community has identified several key capabilities which are currently lacking in the available material models in commercial transient dynamic finite element codes. To attempt to improve the predictive capability of composite impact ...]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 30 May 2017 10:43:07 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004667</guid></item><item><title>Chemical, Structural, and Microstructural Changes in Metallic and Silicon-Based Coating Materials Exposed to Iodine Vapor</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004666</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: The chemical, structural and microstructural behavior of steels (304, 316 and A36), titanium-aluminum alloy (Ti-Al, (6Al-4V)), aluminum-magnesium alloy (Al-Mg, 6061), and coatings (Silcolloy and Dursan (SilcoTek Corporation)) were probed after exposure to iodine laminar flow. Exposures were carried out in a custom-built Iodine Vapor RIG (IVR) at 300 degrees C to an iodine laminar vapor flow of 1 mg min(exp. -1), carried by 145 mL-min(exp. -1) argon gas, for 5, 15 and 30 days. Samples were cha...]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 30 May 2017 10:30:07 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004666</guid></item><item><title>Engine Icing Data - An Analytics Approach</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004522</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: Engine icing researchers at the NASA Glenn Research Center use the Escort data acquisition system in the Propulsion Systems Laboratory (PSL) to generate and collect a tremendous amount of data every day. Currently these researchers spend countless hours processing and formatting their data, selecting important variables, and plotting relationships between variables, all by hand, generally analyzing data in a spreadsheet-style program (such as Microsoft Excel). Though spreadsheet-style analysi...]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2017 11:08:26 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004522</guid></item><item><title>An Overview of Materials Structures for Extreme Environments Efforts for 2015 SBIR Phases I and II</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004521</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: Technological innovation is the overall focus of NASA's Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) program. The program invests in the development of innovative concepts and technologies to help NASA's mission directorates address critical research and development needs for Agency projects. This report highlights innovative SBIR 2015 Phase I and II projects that specifically address areas in Materials and Structures for Extreme Environments, one of six core competencies at NASA Glenn Research ...]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2017 11:02:26 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004521</guid></item><item><title>An Overview of Communications Technology and Development Efforts for 2015 SBIR Phase I</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004519</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: This report highlights innovative SBIR 2015 Phase I projects specifically addressing areas in Communications Technology and Development which is one of six core competencies at NASA Glenn Research Center. There are fifteen technologies featured with emphasis on a wide spectrum of applications such as novel solid state lasers for space-based water vapor dial; wide temperature, high voltage and energy density capacitors for aerospace exploration; instrument for airborne measurement of carbonyl ...]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2017 10:54:26 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004519</guid></item><item><title>Modeling Xenon Tank Pressurization using One-Dimensional Thermodynamic and Heat Transfer Equations</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004518</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: As a first step in understanding what ground support equipment (GSE) is required to provide external cooling during the loading of 5,000 kg of xenon into 4 aluminum lined composite overwrapped pressure vessels (COPVs), a modeling analysis was performed using Microsoft Excel. The goals of the analysis were to predict xenon temperature and pressure throughout loading at the launch facility, estimate the time required to load one tank, and to get an early estimate of what provisions for cooling ...]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2017 10:50:56 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004518</guid></item><item><title>Reversible and Irreversible Time-Dependent Behavior of GRCop-84</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004516</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: A series of mechanical tests were conducted on a high-conductivity copper alloy, GRCop-84, in order to understand the time dependent response of this material. Tensile, creep, and stress relaxation tests were performed over a wide range of temperatures, strain rates, and stress levels to excite various amounts of time-dependent behavior. At low applied stresses the deformation behavior was found to be fully reversible. Above a certain stress, termed the viscoelastic threshold, irreversible de...]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2017 10:40:56 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004516</guid></item><item><title>Increased Jet Noise Due to a "Nominally Laminar" State of Nozzle Exit Boundary Layer</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004649</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: A set of 2-in. diameter nozzles is used to investigate the effect of varying exit boundary layer state on the radiated noise from high-subsonic jets. It is confirmed that nozzles involving turbulent boundary layers are the quietest while nozzles involving a "nominally laminar" boundary layer are loud especially on the high-frequency side of the sound pressure level spectrum. The latter boundary layer state involves a "Blasius-like" mean velocity profile but higher turbulence intensities compa...]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2017 10:24:26 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004649</guid></item><item><title>Method for the Collection, Gravimetric and Chemical Analysis of Nonvolatile Residue (NVR) on Surfaces</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004508</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: Nonvolatile residue (NVR), sometimes referred to as molecular contamination is the term used for the total composition of the inorganic and high boiling point organic components in particulates and molecular films deposited on critical surfaces surrounding space structures, with the particulate and NVR contamination originating primarily from pre-launch operations. The "nonvolatile" suggestion from the terminology NVR implies that the collected residue will not experience much loss under ambi...]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2017 10:11:56 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004508</guid></item><item><title>Increased Jet Noise Due to a "Nominally Laminar" State of Nozzle Exit Boundary Layer</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004650</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: A set of 2-inch diameter nozzles is used to investigate the effect of varying exit boundary layer state on the radiated noise from high-subsonic jets. It is confirmed that nozzles involving turbulent boundary layers are the quietest while nozzles involving a nominally-laminar boundary layer are loud especially on the high-frequency side of the sound pressure level spectrum. The latter boundary layer state involves a Blasius-like mean velocity profile but higher turbulence intensities compared...]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2017 10:07:26 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004650</guid></item><item><title>A Dynamic Calibration Method for Experimental and Analytical Hub Load Comparison</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004507</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: This paper presents the results from an ongoing effort to produce improved correlation between analytical hub force and moment prediction and those measured during wind-tunnel testing on the Aeroelastic Rotor Experimental System (ARES), a conventional rotor testbed commonly used at the Langley Transonic Dynamics Tunnel (TDT). A frequency-dependent transformation between loads at the rotor hub and outputs of the testbed balance is produced from frequency response functions measured during vibr...]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2017 10:06:56 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004507</guid></item><item><title>Unmanned Aircraft Systems Minimum Operations Performance Standards End-to-End Verification and Validation (E2-V2) Simulation</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004506</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: As Unmanned Aircraft Systems (UAS) make their way to mainstream aviation operations within the National Airspace System (NAS), research efforts are underway to develop a safe and effective environment for their integration into the NAS. Detect and Avoid (DAA) systems are required to account for the lack of "eyes in the sky" due to having no human on-board the aircraft. The current NAS relies on pilot's vigilance and judgement to remain Well Clear (CFR 14 91.113) of other aircraft. RTCA SC-228...]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2017 10:05:26 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004506</guid></item><item><title>Wind Tunnel Investigation of Passive Porosity Applied to the Leading-Edge Extension and Leading-Edge Flaps on a Slender Wing at Subsonic Speed</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004505</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: A wind tunnel experiment was conducted in the NASA Langley Research Center 7- by 10-Foot High Speed Tunnel to determine the effects of passive surface porosity on the subsonic vortex flow interactions about a general research fighter configuration. Flow-through porosity was applied to the leading-edge extension, or LEX, and leading-edge flaps mounted to a 65deg cropped delta wing model as a potential vortex flow control technique at high angles of attack. All combinations of porous and nonpor...]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2017 09:50:56 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004505</guid></item><item><title>FIM Avionics Operations Manual</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004502</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: This document describes the operation and use of the Flight Interval Management (FIM) Application installed on an electronic flight bag (EFB). Specifically, this document includes: 1) screen layouts for each page of the interface; 2) step-by-step instructions for data entry, data verification, and input error correction; 3) algorithm state messages and error condition alerting messages; 4) aircraft speed guidance and deviation indications; and 5) graphical display of the spatial relationships...]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2017 09:34:26 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004502</guid></item><item><title>Performance of the Widely-Used CFD Code OVERFLOW on the Pleides Supercomputer</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004382</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: Computational performance studies were made for NASA's widely used Computational Fluid Dynamics code OVERFLOW on the Pleiades Supercomputer. Two test cases were considered: a full launch vehicle with a grid of 286 million points and a full rotorcraft model with a grid of 614 million points. Computations using up to 8000 cores were run on Sandy Bridge and Ivy Bridge nodes. Performance was monitored using times reported in the day files from the Portable Batch System utility. Results for two gr...]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2017 14:24:38 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004382</guid></item><item><title>Cooling of Electric Motors Used for Propulsion on SCEPTOR</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004363</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: NASA is developing a suite of hybrid-electric propulsion technologies for aircraft. These technologies have the benefit of lower emissions, diminished noise, increased efficiency, and reduced fuel burn. These will provide lower operating costs for aircraft operators. Replacing internal combustion engines with distributed electric propulsion is a keystone of this technology suite, but presents many new problems to aircraft system designers. One of the problems is how to cool these electric mot...]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2017 14:13:38 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004363</guid></item><item><title>Approximation of Engine Casing Temperature Constraints for Casing Mounted Electronics</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004365</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: The performance of propulsion engine systems is sensitive to weight and volume considerations. This can severely constrain the configuration and complexity of the control system hardware. Distributed Engine Control technology is a response to these concerns by providing more flexibility in designing the control system, and by extension, more functionality leading to higher performing engine systems. Consequently, there can be a weight benefit to mounting modular electronic hardware on the eng...]]></description><pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2017 12:08:38 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004365</guid></item><item><title>Simulation Evaluation of Pilot Inputs for Real Time Modeling During Commercial Flight Operations</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170003986</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: Aircraft dynamics characteristics can only be identified from flight data when the aircraft dynamics are excited sufficiently. A preliminary study was conducted into what types and levels of manual piloted control excitation would be required for accurate Real-Time Parameter IDentification (RTPID) results by commercial airline pilots. This includes assessing the practicality for the pilot to provide this excitation when cued, and to further understand if pilot inputs during various phases of ...]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2017 13:15:13 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170003986</guid></item><item><title>Peculiarities of Efficient Plasma Generation in Air and Water by Short Duration Laser Pulses</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170003884</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: We have conducted experiments to demonstrate an efficient generation of plasma discharges by focused nanosecond pulsed laser beams in air and provided recommendations on the design of optical systems to implement such plasma generation. We have also demonstrated generation of the secondary plasma discharge using the unused energy from the primary one. Focused nanosecond pulsed laser beams have also been utilized to generate plasma in water where we observed self-focusing and filamentation. Fu...]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 12 May 2017 11:17:56 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170003884</guid></item><item><title>Boron Nitride Nanoribbons from Exfoliation of Boron Nitride Nanotubes</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170003883</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: Two types of boron nitride nanotubes (BNNTs) were exfoliated into boron nitride nanoribbons (BNNR), which were identified using transmission electron microscopy: (1) commercial BNNTs with thin tube walls and small diameters. Tube unzipping was indicated by a large decrease of the sample's surface area and volume for pores less than 2 nm in diameter. (2) BNNTs with large diameters and thick walls synthesized at NASA Glenn Research Center. Here, tube unraveling was indicated by a large increase...]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 12 May 2017 10:55:56 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170003883</guid></item><item><title>Highly Conductive Wire: Cu Carbon Nanotube Composite Ampacity and Metallic CNT Buckypaper Conductivity</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170003881</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: NASA is currently working on developing motors for hybrid electric propulsion applications in aviation. To make electric power more feasible in airplanes higher power to weight ratios are sought for electric motors. One facet to these efforts is to improve (increase) the conductivity and (lower) density of the magnet wire used in motors. Carbon nanotubes (CNT) and composites containing CNT are being explored as a possible way to increase wire conductivity and lower density. Presented here are...]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 12 May 2017 10:40:56 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170003881</guid></item><item><title>Funding and Strategic Alignment Guidance for Infusing Small Business Innovation Research Technology Into Human Exploration and Operations Mission Directorate Projects for 2016</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170003882</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: This report is intended to help NASA program and project managers incorporate Small Business Innovation Research Small Business Technology Transfer (SBIR/STTR) technologies into NASA Human Exploration and Operations Mission Directorate (HEOMD) projects. Other Government and commercial projects managers can also find this useful. Space Transportation; Life Support and Habitation Systems; Extra-Vehicular Activity; High EfficiencySpace Power; Human Exploration and Operations Mission,]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 12 May 2017 10:24:26 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170003882</guid></item><item><title>UAS Reports (UREPs): EnablingExchange of Observation Data Between UAS Operations</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170003878</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: As the volume of small unmanned aircraft systems (UAS) operations increases, the lack of weather products to support these operations becomes more problematic. One early solution to obtaining more information about weather conditions is to allow operators to share their observations and measurements with other airspace users. This is analogous to the AIREP and PIREP reporting systems in traditional aviation wherein pilots report weather phenomena they have observed or experienced to provide b...]]></description><pubDate>Fri, 12 May 2017 10:02:56 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170003878</guid></item><item><title>Analytical Round Robin for Elastic-Plastic Analysis of Surface Cracked Plates, Phase II Results</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004487</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: The second phase of an analytical round robin for the elastic-plastic analysis of surface cracks in flat plates was conducted under the auspices of ASTM Interlaboratory Study 732. The interlaboratory study (ILS) had 10 participants with a broad range of expertise and experience, and experimental results from a surface crack tension test in 4142 steel plate loaded well into the elastic-plastic regime provided the basis for the study. The participants were asked to evaluate a surface crack tens...]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2017 14:16:25 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004487</guid></item><item><title>Installation Torque Tables for Noncritical Applications</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170003491</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: The objective of this project is to define torque values for bolts and screws when loading is not a concern. Fasteners require a certain torque to fulfill its function and prevent failure. NASA Glenn Research Center did not have a set of fastener torque tables for non-critical applications without loads, usually referring to hand-tight or wrench-tight torqueing. The project is based on two formulas, torque and pullout load. Torque values are calculated giving way to preliminary data tables. T...]]></description><pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2017 09:15:47 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170003491</guid></item><item><title>Development and Testing of Harpoon-Based Approaches for Collecting Comet Samples (Video Supplement)</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004092</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: This video supplement contains a set of videos created during the approximately 10-year-long course of developing and testing the Goddard Space Flight Center (GSFC) harpoon-based approach for collecting comet samples. The purpose of the videos is to illustrate various design concepts used in this method of acquiring samples of comet material, the testing used to verify the concepts, and the evolution of designs and testing. To play the videos this PDF needs to be opened in the freeware Adobe ...]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2017 12:43:48 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004092</guid></item><item><title>Development and Testing of Harpoon-Based Approaches for Collecting Comet Samples</title><link>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004091</link><description><![CDATA[Abstract: Comets, having bright tails visible to the unassisted human eye, are considered to have been known about since pre-historic times. In fact 3,000-year old written records of comet sightings have been identified. In comparison, asteroids, being so dim that telescopes are required for observation, were not discovered until 1801. Yet, despite their later discovery, a space mission returned the first samples of an asteroid in 2010 and two more asteroid sample return missions have already been laun...]]></description><pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2017 12:39:18 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://ntrs.nasa.gov/search.jsp?R=20170004091</guid></item></channel></rss>
